http://youtu.be/Rd2BEVNZdDo
http://youtu.be/Rd2BEVNZdDo
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So in this module, as we said, we're going to
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Trong phần này, như đã nói, ta sẽ
look at some fundamental concepts that underlie embedded systems.
học những khái niệm cơ bản làm nền tảng cho hệ thống nhúng.
But before we get to components of an embedded system, we want to get some
Nhưng trước khi đi vào từng bộ phận cấu thành của 1 hệ thống nhúng, ta cần
basics out of the way.
bổ sung vài thứ căn bản.
The first important concept we're going to look at is number systems.
Khái niệm quan trọng đầu tiên là hệ đếm.
That is, all computers use a basic representation for numbers.
Bởi vì tất cả máy tính đều làm việc với những con số.
In order to understand the binary number system, which is what the
Để hiểu được hệ đếm nhị phân, thứ được dùng trên máy tính,
computers use, we'll draw parallels to a system that we are more familiar
ta vẽ 1 bảng so sánh trên hệ đếm mà chúng ta quen thuộc hơn
with-- the decimal number system.
là hệ thập phân.
The decimal number system is sometimes referred to as the base-10 system.
Hệ thập phân, hay còn được gọi là hệ đếm cơ số 10.
A base-10 system has--
1 hệ cơ số 10 có
any system has two important characteristics.
hay bất kỳ hệ đếm nào cũng có 2 đặc tính quan trọng.
That is, each position has a place value.
Mỗi vị trí có 1 giá trị.
That is, when I say that I have a number of--
Đó là khi tôi nói tôi có 1 số
5 digit number, each digit is a position.
5 chữ số, mỗi chữ số là 1 vị trí.
So each position has a place value.
Và mỗi vị trí có 1 giá trị.
And the value attributed to each place is a power of 10, which
Và giá trị ứng với từng vị trí trong cơ số 10 là
is a power of 10.
1 luỹ thừa cơ số 10.
The second characteristic of any number system is, what
Đặc tính thứ 2 trong bất kỳ hệ đếm nào
are the valid values?
những giá trị nào là hợp lệ?
That is, when we--
Đó là khi
the valid values are the coefficients.
Những giá trị hợp lệ là những hệ số.
In the case of the base-10 system, the valid values are 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
Trong trường hợp cơ số 10, những giá trị hợp lệ là 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
7, 8, and 9.
7, 8, và 9.
So for example, when I look at a number like 4723 in base 10-- so we--
Ví dụ, nếu tôi nhìn vào số 4723 trong cơ số 10
to represent a number in base 10, we simply write it this way.
đại diện cho 1 số trong hệ cơ số 10, tôi đơn giản viết nó là
We say that this number represents 4--
Đây là số 4
so each of these positions.
Mỗi số có vị trí của nó.
So we have 4, 7, 2, and 3.
Tôi có 4, 7, 2 và 3.
And three has a place value, which is 10 to the zero.
Số 3 có giá trị vị trí, là 10 mũ 0.
2 has a place value, which is 10 to the one.
2 cũng có 1 giá trị vị trí, là 10 mũ 1.
7 has a place value, which is 10 to the two.
giá trị vị trí của 7 là 10 mũ 2.
And 4 has a place value, which is 10 to the three.
Và của 4 là 10 mũ 3.
So when we add these together, we get the numbers, so which is 4,000,
Kết hợp mọi thứ lại với nhau, ta có những số là 4000,
700, 20, and 3.
700, 20, và 3.
So this number represents 4723 in base 10.
Cho nên số này là 4723 trên cơ số 10.
So let's take a look at the binary number system, which is a base-2
Bây giờ đến hệ nhị phân, hay
number system.
hệ đếm cơ số 2
So again, the first thing is, we have place values, which are powers of 2.
Lần này, đầu tiên, những giá trị vị trí cũng là số mũ của cơ số 2.
And the valid values are 0 and 1.
Giá trị hợp lệ là 0 và 1.
So for example then, if I'm given a number, 1101 to the base 2--
Ví dụ, tôi có 1 số là 1101 trong hệ đếm 2.
so a number, 1101 to the base 2 represents the coefficients
Số này 1101, trong hệ cơ số 2, có các hệ số là
1, 0, 1, and 1.
1, 0 , 1, và 1.
And this 1 has a place value of 2 to the zero.
1 này có giá trị vị trí, là 2 mũ 0
This 0 has a place value of 2 to the one.
của 0 là 2 mũ 1.
This 1 has a place value of 2 to the two.
của 1 này là 2 mũ 2.
And this 1 has a place value of 2 to the three.
Và 1 cuối cùng là 2 mũ 3.
So I add them up.
Cộng chúng lại.
I get an 8 plus a 4, plus that's a 0 times 2 to the one.
Tôi có 8 cộng 4, cộng 0 nhân 2
That's a 0 plus one, which is a 13 in base 10.
Cuối cùng cộng cho 1, nó là số 13 trong hệ đếm 10.
So now that we understand how a base-2 system works and how a base-10 system
Giờ ta đã hiểu hệ cơ số 2 và hệ cơ số 10 hoạt động như thế nào
works, we can actually generalize this to any base.
ta có thể hiểu bất kỳ hệ cơ số nào khác.
For example, if I look at a base-n system, where my--
Ví dụ, tôi có hệ cơ số n
it's n can be either 2 or 10 in this case, then the valid values are going
n có thể là 2 hay 10, giá trị hợp lệ là
to be from 0, 1, 2, all the way up to n minus 1.
0, 1, 2 tới n trừ 1.
So for example here, it's 10 minus 1, which is 9.
Ví dụ, 10 trừ 1 là 9.
Here it is 2 minus 1, which is 1.
2 trừ 1 là 1
So as we move on, any base system can be easily deciphered based on our
Khi ta đi tiếp, hệ đếm nào cũng có thể hiểu được
understanding of what the coefficients are and what the base is.
dựa trên những gì ta thu được từ hệ số và cơ số.